<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The life of Mother Shipton a new comedy as it was acted nineteen dayes together with great applause / written by T.T.</title>
            <author>T. T. (Thomas Thomson), fl. 1668.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1670</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 130 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62423</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1009</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2655</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11950425</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11950425</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51398</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62423)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51398)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 517:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The life of Mother Shipton a new comedy as it was acted nineteen dayes together with great applause / written by T.T.</title>
                  <author>T. T. (Thomas Thomson), fl. 1668.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 56 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by and for Peter Lillicrap, and are to be sold by T. Passenger ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1670?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Shipton, --  Mother --  (Ursula)</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51398:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51398:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Life of Mother Shipton.</p>
            <p>A NEW Comedy.</p>
            <p>As it was Acted Nineteen dayes together with great Applauſe.</p>
            <q>Folia Ampla Sybillae <bibl>
                  <hi>Virg.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Written by <hi>T. T.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by and for <hi>Peter Lillicrap,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>T. Paſſenger</hi> the three Bibles on <hi>London Bridge. 1610.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dramatis_personae">
            <pb facs="tcp:51398:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51398:2"/>
            <head>The Actors Names.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <label>Pluto</label> 
                  <hi>The King of Hell</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Radamon</label> 
                  <hi>A cheif Spirit</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Four other Devils</item>
               <item>The Ab. of <hi>Beverly</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Hairbrain</label> 
                  <hi>A wild Gallant</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Swagger</label> 
                  <hi>His Companion</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Captain</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Shiftwell</label> 
                  <hi>A Pander</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Moneylack</label> 
                  <hi>His Companion</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Sr.</hi> Oliver VVhorehound</label> 
                  <hi>An old Leacher</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>David</label> 
                  <hi>His man</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Roger</label> 
                  <hi>His wifes man</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir.</hi> Ol. VVhorehounds wife going by the name of <hi>Lovefree</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Scrape</label> 
                  <hi>a Uſerer</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mother Shipton</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Abigail</label> her Maid</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Maria</label>
                  <hi>Shiftwels ſiſter</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Priſcilla</label> 
                  <hi>a Whore</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Prue</label> 
                  <hi>a Bawd</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Shiftwels wife</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>And two whores</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The Scenes.</p>
            <p>The City of <hi>York.</hi> OR <hi>Naſebrough Grove</hi> in <hi>Yorkſhire.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="prologue">
            <head>The Prologue.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:51398:3"/>
            <l>PRologues are grown ſo plenty, yet ſo dear</l>
            <l>Our authour choos'd to have no prologue here,</l>
            <l>His is an invitation to a feaſt</l>
            <l>He hopes your ſtomacks will not ill digeſt,</l>
            <l>Yet be not over curious, ſince he has ſpent</l>
            <l>As much as on his Credit could be lent;</l>
            <l>He's not a Poet yet upon his bleſſing</l>
            <l>Has charg'd the Cooks be careful in the dreſsing.</l>
            <l>Expect no choice of dainties of the prime;</l>
            <l>As at the Temple at a reading time,</l>
            <l>Or that our young Cooks are experienc'd ſo</l>
            <l>They can pleaſe every pallat: this we know</l>
            <l>They may in time, then in the mean while</l>
            <l>Grace their endeavours with a courteous ſmile,</l>
            <l>To th' Author and the Actors too prove free,</l>
            <l>Spare not for claps and firſt begin with me.</l>
            <p>
               <hi>Exeunt.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="play">
            <head>The Life of Mother Shipton.</head>
            <div n="1" type="act">
               <head>Act the Firſt,</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>Scene the Firſt.</head>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51398:3"/>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Shipton</hi> ſitting by a Rivers ſide, and <hi>Radamon</hi> a Divel a part.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ship.</speaker>
                     <p>MIſerable <hi>Shipton</hi> in what a poor condition has it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the powers to place thee! ſure all the Eyes of Happineſs did look a Squint at my Nativity, and all the Deſtinies combin'd to wrap me up in end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs poverty.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Di.</speaker>
                     <p>This is excellent her low condition does lay the foundation for my ſiege, i'l liſten to what follows.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ship.</speaker>
                     <p>How pleaſant and thrice happy is the fortune of other Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talls,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51398:4"/>how bravely do they live and injoy themſelves and their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates! How like petty dieties are they ſeated in their pallaces! and to ſuch poor Cottage bred Creatures as my ſelf extend their gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Hoſpitality! how nobly do they paſs over their lives and with odours and perfumes enter their earthly graves, whoſe fame is ſtill ſurviving by their Princely Pedigree? why was not this my lot poor miſerable <hi>Shipton<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Di.</speaker>
                     <p>Better, better yet, ſhe is ambitious, and I am half confident ſhe is my own.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ship.</speaker>
                     <p>What pleaſant life have I? forlorn deſolation? What eſtate or ſubſiſtance? The Alms of the Pariſh? What Grave but a Ditch? And for my pedigree can only boaſt of poverty? I was wretched by my Parents indigency, and by their death in my Minority, thrice, thrice more Miſerable! Am I not fleſh and blood? Has not Nature beſtowed on me the like perfections, each Mortal now can boaſt off? Why am I ſo low then when others are ſo high? Why do I court the ground when others in their glorious pinacles graſp the sky? Well hence forth will I ſcorn their Alms and gifts of Charity.</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Directly or indirectly I will find a way,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>To make me rich in Pride and Money too, but ſtay.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <stage>pauſes.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Di.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Do, do mount higher in ambition yet and then,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thou'lt fall ſo low, thou ne're ſhall riſe again.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ship.</speaker>
                     <p>I am too preſumptuous and do offend theſe powers we are bound in the ſtricteſt obligations to obey: No be content in time thou wilt ſee Heaven will give thee more felicity.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Di.</speaker>
                     <p>Ha! This ſtartles me does her ambition thaw, I'l to her e're ſhe too much repents.</p>
                     <p>Fair Maid, nay ſtartle not, pardon me that I have been a gentle au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditor to your ſorry tale, yet think of me, as I ſeem to be; a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man well deſcended, and not of ſo mean a ſpirit to divulge the leaſt Syllable of what I have heard, but be as ſecret as the ſilent Air.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ship.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir your Carriage and diſcourſe confirm you a Gentleman; and ſince you have over heard what I never intended to declare to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: My hope is in your promiſe: You will be Privy.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:51398:4"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Di.</speaker>
                     <p>I'l be thy boſome Cabinet, and ſince at firſt ſight I ſee thou art meritorious: 'Tis in my power and I am willing to bring thee to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement: Nay ſuch honour as ſhall touch the height of thoſe to whom thou haſt been ſubſervient, and ſpurn at thoſe that hitherto have ſlighted thee.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ship.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir you promiſe fair.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Di.</speaker>
                     <p>I'l perform fairer, Therefore to morrow morn at ſun riſing, under the broad Beech-tree, in <hi>Naeſ-borough</hi> Grove fail not to meet me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ship.</speaker>
                     <p>Upon my Life I will not,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Di.</speaker>
                     <p>Then thou ſhalt ſee, i'l find a means to</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Work thy content, and thereby,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Transform thy ſorrow to felicity</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ship.</speaker>
                     <p>I thank you ſir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Di.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Till then fair Maid farewell,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>This will be good news to the King of Hell.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Radamon.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ship.</speaker>
                     <p>This promiſe makes me proud, perform it &amp; thou art noble</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The Pariſh Alms gifts and Cottages i'l ſcorn</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And no more walk in places ſo forlorn,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>To this Event ye powers grant ſucceſs,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The Sun muſt uſher in my Happineſs.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>Scene the Second.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Shiftwell <hi>and</hi> Moneylack.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>'TIs a mad life thou leadſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>A merry life, the only life? I am like a man finding a Table furniſhed to his hand, as mine is ſtill to me, prayers for the ſounder, I thank him he has maintained my houſe this ſix years, not only keeps my wife, but me and all my family: I am at his Table, he
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51398:5"/>puts me to nothing, no rent, nor Church duties, no not ſo much as the ſcavenger, the happieſt ſtate that ever man was born to: I walk out in a morning, come to breakfaſt, find excellent cheer, a good fire in winter, look in my coal houſe about <hi>Midſomer eve<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi> five or ſix chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drone new laid up<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> look in my back yard, I ſhall find a pile of fagots that over look the Church ſteeple, I ſay nothing to all this, but ſmile and gently pin the door again, when my wife lyes Inn, as even now ſhe's on the point of grunting, a Lady lies not like her, ſhe has her Emboſſings, Embroiderings, Spanglings, and I know not what, her Sugar by whole loaves, her wine by Rundlets: I ſee theſe things but like a haypy man.</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>I pay for none at all, yet fooles think<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>t mine,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>I have the name, and in his Gold I ſhine.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>This charge the Knight has whilſt I without any fear,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Lye ſoft, ſleep hard, drink wine, and eat good chear.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>And then for want of my wife, have I a legion of Miſtreſſes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>But prithee when doeſt exſpect Sir <hi>Oliver?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Why to morrow ſo his laſt letter ſaid.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>So then we may hope for a recruite.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Hope, we will command it, he muſt be liberal to me, but mum here comes <hi>David.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>David.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <p>How now <hi>David</hi> any newes for me from Sir <hi>Oliver</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, I have a Letter for you Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>He is in good health I hope.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                     <p>I hear nothing to the contrary, but I muſt bid you farewell Sir, buſineſs calls me away, otherwiſe Mr. <hi>Shiftwel</hi> you and I would not part ſo driely.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Farewel honeſt <hi>David</hi>
                     </p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Exit</hi> David</stage>
                     <p>So now Ile open thee.</p>
                     <stage>Reads.</stage>
                     <p>My dear <hi>Shiftwel.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>That's lovingly.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>O 'tis flattery I fear</p>
                     <p>In the laſt you received from me, I told thee how ſpeedy I would be in my return, both for the love I bear to my Lady and thy ſelf,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:51398:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>but ſince ſeveral buſineſſes prohibite my intent, ſo that now I cannot be in town till the latter end of next week, but then I will be moſt liberal</p>
                     <stage>Sir <hi>Oliver Whorehound.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>This does not make the old Proverb good, <hi>ſhort and ſweet,</hi> for this is ſhort</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>But damnable ſower.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>Well poverty parts good company, ſo for the preſent fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel, next time we meet, I hope we ſhall be in a condition too fare better.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Moneylack.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shif.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Fear not for I do live without regard,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The pander needs muſt have a free reward,</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <head>Scen. III.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter Mrs.</hi> Lovefree <hi>and</hi> Roger <hi>her man with a port<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantle<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Io.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>ROger</hi> earry the Portmantle to my Lodging, Ile follow preſently.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                     <p>I will forſooth.</p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Exit</hi> Roger.</stage>
                     <p>Ha <hi>Noll,</hi> is it ſo i'faith has a young Mrs, reſtored a new fire into your decayed parts, I thought 'twas impoſſible for nature to broach another veſſel of ſtrength into thy whithered veins, well if it be ſo, ſo let it be: when I lay by thy ſide thou tookeſt no care in the night but to mumble out thy prayer and <hi>Pater noſter:</hi> many times when I have endeavoured to force a motion in thee, to give life to thy dead ſpirits alas! I was anſwered wiith hollow groans, and excuſes of age? and to imagine the truth, I beleive tis rather thy money then thy for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude that quenches the appetite of that woman thou frequents for otherwiſe by experience I can tell her thirſt would rather encreaſe then her deſire be ſatisfied: well Ile pay thee in thy Coyn, I have not a face altogether contemptible, nor money for properties to preſerve it from wrinckles, and I hope ere long this City will afford me a Gallant.</p>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:51398:6"/>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Whore-hound <hi>revenge is counted no diſgrace.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Cuckold thy horns will quickly bud apace,</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="scene">
                  <head>Scen IV.</head>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Pluto Proſerpina</hi> and five Devils.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Plu.</speaker>
                     <p>MY brave ſpirits the world is now in diſtraction, confuſion meets in every place, and will ere long involve it ſelf into a ſecond <hi>Chaos:</hi> now with all the helliſh art you are maſters of, ſcout about and make the conſciences of men as black as Hell it ſelf: mean while <hi>Alecto</hi> let it be your care to cheriſh our Traytors in the lower vault. <hi>Maſſanello</hi> that proud fiſher boy that durſt uſurp ſo much diſloyalty againſt his Prince, to raiſe forces againſt him and make his ſubjects moſt perfidious, the like to <hi>Matchavile</hi> that whead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Traytor, <hi>Synon</hi> that betrayed the noble <hi>Trojans,</hi> alſo to <hi>Hanibal</hi> the nobleſt Hellhound Hell can boaſt of, but who comes here.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Radamon.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                     <p>Great Prince 'tis <hi>Radamon.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Plu.</speaker>
                     <p>Now <hi>Radamon</hi> the news with thee.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Great prince the news I bring,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Will make your Queen and all our Furies ſing.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Plu.</speaker>
                     <p>Declare it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                     <p>I have been with <hi>Shipton</hi> a poor Alms wench to whom as ſhe was deploring her ſad condition, I appeared apparelled like a very handſome Gentleman, gave her large promiſes, to make good which early this Morn, at Sun-riſing I am to meet her under the broad Beech tree in <hi>Na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>sborough</hi> Grove.</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Then I do not doubt</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>To make effectual what I have been about.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Plu.</speaker>
                     <p>Well done <hi>Radamon</hi> thou art a providing Divel and does much
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51398:6"/>for the Intereſt of our Kingdom, we thank thee for thy care and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Come now lets revel and with ſuch delight</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>We'l ſpend the tedious minutes of this night.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[They Dance, dance ended]</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Plu.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Now we'l go viſit our Helveechans that have been</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Inrichers of our Kingdom by their ſin.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="scene">
                  <head>Scene the Fifth.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Shiftwell <hi>and Mr.</hi> Scrape <hi>ſeverally.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>NOw for <hi>Moneylack</hi> he'l behold and bleſs himſelf, and with confidence ſwear i'm a limb of a Devil. How <hi>Scrape</hi> one of my old Uſurers! Pox on his picture! Now do I quake as if I had had the ſtanding Ague theſe ſeven years! yet perforce I muſt be couragious and ſpeak to him: Mr. <hi>Scrape</hi> your obleiged Servant Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Scra.</speaker>
                     <p>Mr. <hi>Shiftwel</hi> how have you done this long while, I can never have the happineſs to ſee you at our end of the town.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>No faith nor never ſhall <stage>Aſide</stage> as long as I can keep at this.</p>
                     <p>Why Sir, ſo and ſo, I make a heard ſhift to keep head and ſhould<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders together.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Scra.</speaker>
                     <p>Well but to put off this diſcourſe, you and I muſt be a little more ſerious.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Now it begins to work.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Scra.</speaker>
                     <p>You know Mr. <hi>Shiftwell,</hi> the times expired my money due, and your bond forfeited, and now what would you have me do? when I lent my money I appeare an Angel, but now I call for it again Ile war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant you a very devil.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>'Fleſh! what ſhall I do with him? ther's no way to ſet him going but Hectoring. Why Sir I can't help it, you muſt ſtay till I have it, you know like a Gentleman I pawn'd you my Land for the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51398:7"/>tenth part of the value, and now times are dead, no money ſtirring, 'tis a bard caſe, you muſt forbear longer or I ſhall grow very angry.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Scrap.</speaker>
                     <p>Fret and ſpare not, I know no obligation lies upon me with my honey to feed drones, but in ſhort my money I want, and my money ile have, or it ſhall go hard with you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shif.</speaker>
                     <p>Fleſh how the Rogue railes <stage>Aſide</stage> ſure he has got ſome Baliffes nigh; I ſee none: <stage>Looks out</stage> yet its well, he knowes not of my being a Pander, therefore Ile plead poverty, and my former trade of Merchandize, and ſee if I can move the Rogue to pitty: alas! at preſent Sir I cannot, my wife and fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly then will ſtarve for want of bread.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Scrap.</speaker>
                     <p>More too blame thou in not providing better to ſupport them, your debt is an eſtate for a good man pray acquaint me how were my thouſand pounds imployed?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Moneylack.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>How a Dun upon <hi>Shiftwel,</hi> I am come to my wiſh, here Il<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> keep out of ſight and hear all, I know no object that could more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent me. Ha my Uncle <hi>Scrape,</hi> better and better, but Ile be ſilenced till the future.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t not on my Calamity good Sir, though being a Debtor and a ſlave to him that lends, I muſt endure it, yet hear me ſpeak thus much in my own defence, loſſes at ſea, and thoſe Sir, great and many by ſtorms and tempeſt, not domeſtical Riot in ſoothihg of my wifes humor, or my own has brought me to this low ebb.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>Sure tis an old debt, he pleads his former trade of Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize, 'tis well the old Rogue knows it to be no otherwiſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Scrap.</speaker>
                     <p>Suppoſe this true.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shif.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay 'tis a real truth without ſuppoſals Sir, beſides can you think in your unqueſtioned wiſdome that the ruine of me, (once an able Merchant) can raiſe your reputation with good men!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>No if it thrive with him, hang me as 'twill damne him if he be not converted, for all he's my Uncle.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shif.</speaker>
                     <p>Suppoſe this Sir, if you permit me a moneth more, it wi l not be your loſs nor prejudice, and there was never yet but ſhame and ſcandal in a victory when Rebels unto reaſons paſſion fought it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:51398:7"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>Our Divines cannot ſpeak more effectually.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Scrap.</speaker>
                     <p>Shall I be talked out of my Money.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shif.</speaker>
                     <p>No Sir, but entreated to do your ſelf a benefit and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve that you poſſeſs intire.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Scrap.</speaker>
                     <p>How Friend?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shif.</speaker>
                     <p>By makeing me your beadsman, when I eat my thanks, next Heaven, will be paid to your mercy, when your ſhips are at ſea, my prayers will ſwell the ſailes with proſperous winds and guard them from tempeſts and Pyrates: keep your ware houſes from fire, or quench them with my tears.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Scrap.</speaker>
                     <p>If this could be.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>It muſt or my devotion lyes: <stage>Aſide.</stage> come Sir, I ſee a gentle promiſe in your eye, make it a happy act and me rich in being the inſtrument.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Scrap.</speaker>
                     <p>Well you have prevailed, take a moneth longer, but ſee you faile not, if you do Ile proteſt you firſt, and that done, have the Statute made for Bankrupts ſerved upon you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shif.</speaker>
                     <p>If I do 'tis in your power, but not in mine to ſhun it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Scrap.</speaker>
                     <p>But do you hear: no talk of it, ſhould this arrive at twelve on the exchange, I ſhould be laugh'd at for my fooliſh pitty, which money men hate, ſo farewel.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shif.</speaker>
                     <p>So he's gone. <stage>Looks out.</stage> I bleſs the Counter where I learnt this Rhetorick, now Ile ſhake againe.</p>
                     <stage>ſhakes his Pockets.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>Ha! ſo full faith and plead poverty, Ile out and ſcorn him: Ha, ha, ha.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shif.</speaker>
                     <p>Well Ile abide your jears for once, and hope it may be your turne another time.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>In troth very likely, but I have ſeen and heard all, excuſe my manners.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shif.</speaker>
                     <p>I think I worked him pretty well for all he was your Uncle,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay and with ſuch Devotion too.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shif.</speaker>
                     <p>Never did I pray ſo, ſo heartily before,</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>But come now lets to the next Tavern steer,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And there my hoarſe pipes with Canary cleer;</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="scene">
                  <head>Sceen the ſixth,</head>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:51398:8"/>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Shipton.</stage>
                  <p>PUft up with pride I am grown ambitious, can I forget to give, a bow to the humble Milkmaids: can I forget a curſie making to my liberal Almes-givers? can I forget every Sundaies going to the Church porch to beg a loaf? yes I can forget all,</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Shipton <hi>no more now ſhall be,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Beholding to their liberallity.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>But ha! I ſee my happineſs, the Sun ſhines clear: come, come my worthy Gallant, if thou doſt faile to effect what thou haſt promiſed me, all my expectations are but Aire! but why do I doubt thy gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, I am confident in thy nobleneſs, and will vaunt upon it: ſoare high <hi>Shipton,</hi> higher yet, and think thou never waſt, what too ſure thou haſt been! Ha, ha, ha, me thinks I ſhall laugh to ſee a poor wench beging for an Almes, though I have don't my ſelf, ha! for that very word I could correct my inſolence! I will avouch I neere was poor: hang all beggarry, for my expected happineſs aſſures me I was born to know endleſs felicity, not the fruits of woe. But ſtranger things I yet conceive! This Gentleman could not having no ground of acquaintance promiſe me this preferment without a cauſe? no my youth and beauty ſtirr'd him to't! I am in my teens and that alone muſt be the motive! this I conjecture, and this effect ye powers for my future bliſs.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Radamant <hi>with two other Devils like Gentlemen.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rad.</speaker>
                     <p>My pritty Damſel I muſt confeſs I have been ſomewhat tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, but now come to perform my promiſe beyond thy expectation, gueſs at my meaning.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ship.</speaker>
                     <p>Alas! I cannot propheſie Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:51398:8"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                     <p>Then know I intend to marry thee, and have brought theſe my attendants to witneſſe it</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ship.</speaker>
                     <p>Are you real Sir?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                     <p>By all that's real I am: behind this Grove I have a horſe and pillion for my Spouſe, theſe my attendants are nobly mounted too, we have not Jades that need the ſwitch and ſpur, but will run with all ſpeed to performe the rights that to our marriage ſhall be appur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant, beſtow thy ſelf upon me and all my Fortunes and Eſtate are thine.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ship.</speaker>
                     <p>Now I ſee I propheſied rightly: I am ever happy, Thee and thy eſtate, a noble Husband.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                     <p>A match lets go,</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>But firſt joyn hands that nothing may our he arts devide.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>I am thy bridegroom.</hi> Ship. <hi>And I am thy Bride.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt,</stage>
                  <trailer>Finis <hi>Actus Primi.</hi>
                  </trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="act">
               <head>Actus ſecundus.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>Scena prima.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Greg. Hodge. Jug. <hi>and</hi> Bab. <hi>Beggars.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>COme, come devide the ſpoyle, ſhare and ſhare like<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Greg.</speaker>
                     <p>Withall my heart: there <hi>Hodge</hi> there's for thee.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>Very right.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Greg.</speaker>
                     <p>And there <hi>Jug</hi> there's for thee.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Jug.</speaker>
                     <p>True to a farthing.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Greg.</speaker>
                     <p>And there <hi>Bab's</hi> for thee, and here's for my ſelf, and the odd <hi>overplus</hi> lets give to the Fidler.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>A very good Motion, for now after our long puritanical praying lets ſpend a little of what we got in meriment.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Jug.</speaker>
                     <p>Prethee <hi>Greg.</hi> what is it thou ſtareſt at ſo?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Greg.</speaker>
                     <p>Why at yonder thach't cottage, me thinks it would make a
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:51398:9"/>pretty pallace for us Princes of the ragged Regiment to in habite in.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>O that was old <hi>Shipton</hi> the ditch diggers.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Jug.</speaker>
                     <p>I but he is dead, <hi>Hodge,</hi> and has left it to his daughter a poor Almes wench.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bab.</speaker>
                     <p>And yet as proud as the Devil.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Jug.</speaker>
                     <p>I wonder what's become of her, I have not ſeen her at Almes giving a pretty while, and ſhe did not uſe to hang an Arſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>Piſh let her be where ſhe will, we keep the Fidler here to no purpoſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Greg.</speaker>
                     <p>Well ſtrike up Fidler wee'l take a dance, and then make en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry after <hi>Agatha Shipton</hi> for the purchaſe of her cottage.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>A Song.
<lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>A Beggars a Prince, we gather from hence</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>VVe are not confined as ſome Princes be,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Though we are not ſo rich,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>VVee've as princely an Itch,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And my mind, my mind is a Kingdome to me,</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>We looſe no grate purſes,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Nor have not the Curſes,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Of Orphans: of Widdows, or poor Caveliers,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And before that I ſhall, from a Dignity fall,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>'Till be eight times, nine times ten hundred years.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>We ſcorn all their fears,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And live not in fears,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Of being impriſoned by black rod or Tower,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And as for the ſtocks, of it ſelf it unlocks</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Within the ſpace of a mery ſhort hour,</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </stage>
                  <stage>Dance and <hi>Exeunt.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>Act ſecond, Scen. ſecond.</head>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:51398:9"/>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter the</hi> Captain <hi>Solus.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <p>I that have lead a life until of late in ſpight of death, paſſed through the dangers of it without regard, am now won and vanquiſhed: There is an heroick Amazon hard by, whoſe eyes have darted fire in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomy breaſt, which nothing but her kindneſs can extinguiſh, but if ſhe ſhould prove cruel I ſhall ſoon be aſhes I Muſt I thus yeild? ſhall I forget the ſound of Martial drums, the warlike noiſe of Trumpets, to liſt to the inticeing harmony of inſtruments touched by <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ikellas</hi> hand? ſhall I forget the ordering of a camp? to ride great horſes to beſiedgs a City? to undermine a Caſtle, to raiſe Bulwarks, and all for the love of a ſimple woman? it muſt be ſo: theſe legs that were wont to lead arm'd men to battaile, I now muſt uſe in dances: this haire that uſed to be covered with a Helm cloggy with ſweat and blood, I now muſt daily powder: theſe hands that were uſed to wave a dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſword inſtead of iron gauntlets, now muſt wear perfumed gloves: I that was wont to be conſtantly under a Chyrurgeons hands, muſt have a Barber now to keep me neat: O Love thou art divine, and canſt transforme,</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>A man from that he was, it is in vain,</l>
                     <l>Tn think to ſhun the thieg thou doſt conſtrain.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>O heaven if I can but win my love, it will be a conqueſt deſerves a trophee far above,</p>
                  <p>My beſt of victories:
<q>
                        <l>Ile go and try her,</l>
                        <l>'Twas love that kindled, love muſt quench my fire.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Roger.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
                     <p>Who art thou,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                     <p>I Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
                     <p>I you, what are you to good to be ſpoke too?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                     <p>I am <hi>Roger.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
                     <p>By that I know thee not, is <hi>Roger</hi> in a Captains Roll? iſt't writ?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes Sir in the Parſons book; the day thereof my baptiſme is ſet down.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:51398:10"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
                     <p>And in that honour, how oft haſt thou ere fought with Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels and kil'd a ſcore or two.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ro,</speaker>
                     <p>Not I, a ſcore or two ſaid you Captaine, nay then I ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver eſcape, for ile promiſe you many one is hang'd for killing of one.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
                     <p>Fie what an ignorance is this haſt thou a mind to become a ſouldier?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                     <p>Indeed I cannot reſolve you, I am with a Miſtreſs, ile ask her whether ſhee'l turn ſouldier too, and then if I like it there's an end, but pray Captain what is a ſouldier?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
                     <p>A ſouldier is a man that ventures his life a hundred times a day, and in his Princes and his Countries cauſe ſtands Canons ſhot, and when his bodies full of wounds, lyes all night in the field, and ſleeps upon his Helm.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                     <p>Good Captain pardon me, neither I nor my Miſtreſs will be ſouldiers then, venter my life ſo many times a day, there's more ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in turning Theif, marry I thought a ſouldier had not been ſuch a fool, but now I think on't good Captain perſwade my Father, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Brothers, Siſters, and all the kindred I have to become ſouldiers, that they may all be killed quickly, I ſwear Captain you ſhould looſe nothing by it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
                     <p>Baſe Coward.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                     <p>Good Sir what is the meaning of that word Coward?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
                     <p>A Coward is a fellow as baſe as thou, one that does ſpend his pretious time in ſloath, cares not what alterations Kingdomes have, ſo be at home may welter in his pleaſures, a fellow that had rather ſit all day ſmoaking Tobaco and carouſeing cups, then dye his ſword in blood of Enemies.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                     <p>Why then Sir indeed I am a very Coward, 'tis better by half then a ſouldier, I know there's far more pleaſure in a glaſs of good wine then in bullets whizing about ones ears, and Pikes and Halberts beating out ones teeth.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou dungil wretch.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay pray Sir be not angry, for I vow I ſhould never digeſt the ſouldiers life.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou earthen minded ſlave 'tis pitty thou ſhould'ſt eat or drink thou haſt no better thoughts.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:51398:10"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ro,</speaker>
                     <p>Good Sir give me leave to be of my own mind and a Coward, I am ſure there's no wiſe man but won'd ſay as I doe, what have I to do with ſouldery, let thoſe follow wars that at are weary of their lives.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou art as dungil a minded Raſcal as ever I heard, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveſt to be hang'd, and ſo I leave thee.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Captain.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                     <p>Go hang your ſelf my Hufting Captain, what have I to do with your warrs two, I ſhould never endure to hear a gun ſhot off, for hearing the report of our Stewards piſtol, does many times make me endanger my breeches.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <head>Scen. Third.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Shipton <hi>with Attendants.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ship.</speaker>
                     <p>Stand at a diſtance, me thinks this ſtate becomes me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> a Cryer.</stage>
                  <p>HA! what Bell is that?</p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cry.</speaker>
                     <p>O Yes, if any man or woman, in City, Town, or Country can tell me tydings of <hi>Agatha Shipton,</hi> the daughter of <hi>Solomon Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> Ditch digger lately deceaſed, let them bring word to the Cryer of the Village, and they ſhall be well rewarded for their pains.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ship.</speaker>
                     <p>Curſe on that tongue what makes this cry after me? can they not beſtow the Almes that came to my ſhare to ſome other poor wretch that wants it more then I do now? no 'tis not that! upon my life ſome canting Beggars covetuous of my cottage have made this way of inquiry for me to purchaſe it. And if my noble Lord ſhould have divulged it to theſe my attendants what I firſt was, and they now declare it I ſhould again be wretched for all theſe delicates: I can't in my proud thought be rich if any but himſelf ſhould know I ever was poor.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:51398:11"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cry.</speaker>
                     <p>Pray ean any here tell me tydings of the party I cry off?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Att.</speaker>
                     <p>No truly honeſt man.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cry.</speaker>
                     <p>Then farewell Gentlemen.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ship.</speaker>
                     <p>This anſwer does agen prop up my ſpirit.</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>My worthy ſervants know me or know me not<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                           </hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>This preſent kindneſs never ſhall be forgot.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Radamon.</stage>
                  <p>Welcome Noble Sir.</p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                     <p>I hankes my fair Spouſe, I ſee I am come moſt opertunely, lets ſit and taſte of all the varieties this board is furniſhed with.</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>—<hi>Attendants in the mean while</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Let your dancing make our Lady ſmile.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>(Sit at a banquet) <hi>They dance,</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                     <p>Now begone, wee muſt conferre in private. Now I am thy Husband and thou art my Wife, yet know I am no mortal! I am a Devil! theſe my attendants Devils too! I can peirce through the aire, ranſack its Treaſures! I can raiſe thunder and lightning, ſtir up Storms, quell Tempeſts, do or undo any thing to pleaſe me! Ile give thee power too! the windes ſhall be at thy command, and every thing elſe at thy diſpoſe!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ship.</speaker>
                     <p>How matried to an Imaterial Spirit this ſtarteles me, how ſweetly could I now deſire my former poverty! but Pride aſſures me I am happy ſtill, and on that ſtaff ile lean. Then Fortune turn thy wheel,</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>I am in now and muſt through,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And to all virtuous acts I bid adiev.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>Well having cunningly wone me to you, I muſt obey and be what you are pleaſed to make me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                     <p>Then after me repeat theſe following words.</p>
                     <q>Raziel, Ziragia, Phonthonfancia.</q>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ship,</speaker>
                     <p>Repeats.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Both</hi> Exeunt <hi>with Thunder and Ligtning,</hi>
                  </stage>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="scene">
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:51398:11"/>
                  <head>Scene the Fourth</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Shiftwel <hi>and</hi> Roger.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                     <p>I Shall ſtudy to be your humble ſervant.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou art a noble Miniſter of words: but wilt thou be my Cabinet, my friend <hi>Roger?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                     <p>I will obey you Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Liberally ſpoken, when I have opened me, wilt thou be privy?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                     <p>Very ſecret and officious, it is manners in me, your commands ſhall wedge my tongue, hedge my heart, and tye a true Lovers knot with the ſtrings of it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou art an honeſt clad of earth, it is pitty the malitious Sun-ſhine warm'd thee not into a Diamond.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                     <p>You ſpeak above my brain Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>I am marvellouſly in love with your Lady, <hi>Roger.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                     <p>Wonderful! is my Lady your ſweet heart?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes but ignorant of my affection yet.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                     <p>I would be drunk if you were my Maſter Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>I <hi>Roger,</hi> I would have a Wine cellar to the purpoſe Man, but doſt know any poſſible way to win her?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir I am paſſing empty of invention: but an't pleaſe you would you marry her?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>No you may ſwear it, but I muſt counterfeit yes, why doſt wonder at it?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                     <p>She does nothing all day but read merry Comedies, and every night ſpend two or three houres on a Tragedy of a merry fellow <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metas,</hi> and a company of ſtrange nam'd Lovers, ſhe's no more a hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife then you or I Sir, on my own proper knowledge I vow and proteſt it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou art too earneſt my old fac'd <hi>Saturn,</hi> I like her near the worſe, huswifery is the ſuperficies of a gentle Female, and the paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis of a Lady which may be well left out.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:51398:12"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                     <p>You are a ſchollar Sir, and your bookſhip ſhall direct me,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſhould be glad to cope with your Lady Sir, me thinks I am of a prompter expreſſion then uſal: Ha! your Lady ſaid I? faith ſee where ſhe comes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter Mrs.</hi> Lovefree.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                     <p>I vaniſh in a miſt then.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Roger.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>He out with a Poetical Solique for my <hi>Praeludium.</hi> The gaudy ſtars are not more full of glee, when golden <hi>Phaebus</hi> ſetteth in the <hi>Weſt,</hi> nor doe the chearful Birds with more delight rejoyce at the new livery of the ſpring, then I to have this Miracle of Beauty enter into the knowledge of my Eyes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs <hi>Love.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>He ſpeaks well, I would he meant in earneſt, the gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſeems very deſerving, but hee's ſomewhat wild I imagine.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>She ſhall be ſtoutly accoſted, impudence is a very happy quality in a wooer I perceive.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs <hi>Love.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>He comes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Lady I credit you are not a puny in the Court of <hi>Cupid,</hi> and therefore I hope need not the tedious circumſtances of an Annual ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice: I am bold to tell you plainly I love you, and if I find occaſion I will maintain it boldly.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs <hi>Love.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Pray Sir Deſiſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Never, ſweet Lady, my deſcent I know you doubt not, and my love you need not, for while I live I ſhall love you, and when you dye your memory.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs <hi>Love.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Your carriage and diſcourſes Sir, ſhew you are a Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veller.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>My boldneſs ſhe means: Madam I have been one and can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the Habits, Conditions and Scituations of diverſe Countries; nay more my fornights obſervation of the <hi>Antipodes,</hi> this will make her wonder.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs <hi>Love.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>O ſtrange have you been there Sir? I admire how you ever came thither!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Madam I can tell you, but ſhould I tell you, I ſhould afright you more then the doleful groans of a dying Creature in the hideous night.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:51398:12"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs <hi>Love.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Nay if it be ſo terrible, pray ſir forbear.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Well put off.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs <hi>Love.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Yet, pray reſolve me one thing.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>No ſooner asked but granted.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs <hi>Love.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Whether the Antipodes have a King.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes but he's no man.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs <hi>Love.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>I beleive ſo, for I could never credit that any man in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habited there.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift,</speaker>
                     <p>There they have no houſes neither but the Kings pallace, where Sir <hi>Francis Drake</hi> was entertained after he had ſhot the gulf.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs <hi>Love.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Poſſible! I wonder at it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay more they at the <hi>Antipodes</hi> hear with their noſes, ſmel with their ears, but taſte withall their ſences, for they are the moſt inſatiableſt gluttons in the whole world.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs <hi>Love.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>But I cannot imagine how their ſences are ſo contrary to ours,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay and they are oppoſite to us too.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs <hi>Love.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>That indeed I have heard. But you frequent playes, do ye not ſir?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Playes they are moſt commonly my every afternoons recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs <hi>Love.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>And you have red many Hiſtories?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Many Lady.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs <hi>Love.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>This pleaſes me too, farewel ſir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Admired Lady leave me not ſo.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs <hi>Love.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>What would you have ſir?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Your conſent Lady</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs <hi>Love.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>O expect that hereafter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay dear Lady.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs <hi>Love.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>You are too importunate ſir farewel.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>No matter, I am ſure to have thee: how ſome women are taken with ſtrange tales? queſt onleſs ſhe's a Widdow, but no matter, plenty of money will weave contempt in a beauty at ſecond hand.</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Next time we meet I do not doubt to get her,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Hercules <hi>could not wooe a Lady better.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:51398:13"/>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Monylack.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Money-lack.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou art well met.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>Thanks good <hi>Shiftwel.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>I have brave newes to tell thee, but come let's to the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern, and by the virtue of a glaſs of wine, 'twil ſlide off my tongue more ſweet.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>Agreed, but I ſhould call upon a friend about this hour ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to engagement.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay ile not ſtay for 'tis full noon, and I have promiſed to be Sir <hi>Olivers</hi> gueſs.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>Hee's come to town then.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes he came laſt night, and has commanded noble prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for the goſſiping to day. Ha! ſee where he comes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Sir <hi>Oliver,</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>Ile leave you then.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Proteſt but you ſhan't, Sir <hi>Oliver</hi> the humbleſt of your ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Oliver.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Nephew <hi>Shiftwel.</hi> the only one I wiſht for.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift</speaker>
                     <p>You are welcome to town Sir, I expected you long afore this, till your laſt Letter ſhew'd good cauſe to the contray.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Oliver,</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Indeed I could not poſſible come till now, nor now neither well, for in the interim ſeveral concerns of mine lyes in the truſt and confidence of ſome perſons which I doubt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Your Lady Sir is delivered of a fine plump boy, he will be as notable a wag as the Father Ile watrant him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Oliver.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>I have ſeen it and bleſſed it, but to make my promiſe good, there Nephew ther's ten peices for you, and come you muſt be my principal gueſs to day.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>It grieves me that I muſt be forced againſt my will, I hate the company of ſuch a crew of Women (as there to be ſure I ſhall find enow) nay and honeſt women too: yet for this moneys ſake I muſt, and ſo good patience guide me, Sir I can't deny you, but this Gentleman is my intimate friend and in leaving him ſo abruptly, I make a breach of our friendſhip,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:51398:13"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Oliver.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Not for the world, with this Gentleman your friend, I invite you for my gueſs to day, and will promiſe you Sir a hearty wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir I thank you, but would willingly beg your pardon and my excuſe, for probablely my ſtrangeneſs may be ſome part of hindrance to mirth in ſome of your ſcotiable gueſs,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Oliver.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Not in the leaſt Sir, I have a Neice that loves to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſuch handſome Gentlemen as you are.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>He means my Siſter <hi>Maria,</hi> faith for that words ſake goe <hi>Money-lack.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Oliver.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Nay pray Sir come, no more delayes.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>My Gueſs by this are ſate and dinner stayes!</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="scene">
                  <head>Scen. fifth.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Pluto Proſerpina, <hi>and five Devils.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pluto.</speaker>
                     <p>NOw declare,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1 <hi>Div.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Infernal King, I have been my circuit, but each chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians heart was ſo fortyfied againſt my attempts, that I was dubious of bringing any news acceptable to your ear, till at laſt creeping in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſtrong water ſhop amongſt a crew of topers, I partly divided my ſelf and ſtuck upon each mans tongue, who preſently within the ſpace of a poor moment, warpt out ſuch a number of ignominous lyes, that Hell it ſelf would quake to hear them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2 <hi>Di.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>I was his ſecond, for in a puffe of ſmoak I crep up their noi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils into their very brain, and their plaid a tyrants part in convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their lies into execrable Oathes: damnation was their conſtant wiſh, and ſo wiſh I and hope ere long to make them <hi>Charons</hi> cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>3 <hi>Di.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>I have been amongſt a crew of Coblers and Broom-men and have raiſed an endleſs diſcord, that I dare promiſe upon penalty of your powerful diſpleaſure, diverſity of murders will be between them committed.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>4 <hi>Di.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>I have not been idle neither: I have been ſcouting among
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:51398:14"/>the Lawyers in their pleading hall, where a cauſe coming to be heard between a rich Uſerer and an Heir, I skipt into the hearts of ſix affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>davit men, who ſwore point blanck for the Uſerers intereſt, againſt what was either truth or equity which makes for the intereſt of our Kingdom.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pluto.</speaker>
                     <p>Well 'twas bravely done, and for this your care and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence kiſs our <hi>Proſerpines</hi> hand, then run to your ſeveral ſtations to perfect what you have partly i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tangled: if you meet any of your,</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Other to brethren, bid them make haſte to bring</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>A fraught of ſoules to Hells fiery King.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  <trailer>Finis Actus Secundi.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="act">
               <head>Act Third,</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>Scen the Firſt.</head>
                  <stage>Shipton <hi>deformed in her Cottage.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <p>AM I awake or in a dream? Ha! What dingy Hayloft am I left in now? Am I once more become the miſerable Inhabitant of my poor paternal Cottage: Alas! 'tis too true! Is this the end of all my pride to be again reduced to my priſtine poverty! How vain is ſeeming glory! How momentary are all the pleaſures that airy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits boaſt off! Decitful Devil am I thy Spouſe and ſo a witch and have no other habitation but where deriſion daily laughs me in the face, Why doſt thou not build me Caſtles in the Air that I might throw down Thunder bolts upon the heads of thoſe that durſt up braid me? But ha! whats this! O helliſh Cruelty! Am I <hi>Agatha Shipton,</hi> ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly no! Where's thy captivating beauty did inchant inſinuating Divels! Here's nothing left but the bare bones of a decayed face of four-ſcore years of Age which verifies the Proverb ſhe looks as if the <hi>Hag had red her:</hi> Then farewel all future expectation of true felicity I muſt,</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Perforce conform my ſelf now to embrace</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The ſpells of utter darkneſs and diſgrace.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <stage>Enter.</stage>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:51398:14"/>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Beggars.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Greg.</speaker>
                     <p>How now runaway are you once more come to light agen?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ship.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes Hellibore.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Greg.</speaker>
                     <p>Bore me no Bores d'you ſee you are a Sow for boring of me for all your crooked Noſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Jug.</speaker>
                     <p>Bleſs me ſhe is ſtrangely altered!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bab.</speaker>
                     <p>Sure 'tis not ſhe!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
                     <p>Sure my Name is not <hi>Hodge:</hi> Come we come to bid you Money for the purchaſe of your Cottage.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ship.</speaker>
                     <p>Keep your Money I want it not, nor any thing elſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Jug.</speaker>
                     <p>Marry come up Potters are you grown ſo proud, I have known the time you would have leapt at a cruſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ship.</speaker>
                     <p>Tormentors be gone and trouble me not.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Greg.</speaker>
                     <p>Be gone, we won't or if we do we will ſend a whole Legion of Admirators to perplex thee, all the Country ſhall know of thy Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viliſh deformity.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ship.</speaker>
                     <p>Are you preſumptuous villanies.</p>
                     <stage>ſtamps</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Radamon <hi>with Thunder and Lightning and ſcares away the Beggars.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rad.</speaker>
                     <p>Now am I come to ſupply the Company of thoſe thou wiſe'y haſt dismiſt and in recompence of my love thou muſt practice Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Witchcraft, fatal Propheſies and what not that Hell can boaſt off.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ship.</speaker>
                     <p>My former vows enforce me to enact what you deſire.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Then i'l promiſe thee: Henceforward thou ſhalt be</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Admired by Nations for thy Prophecy.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt <hi>with horrid Muſick,</hi>
                  </stage>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:51398:15"/>
                  <head>Scene the Second.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Sir Oliver <hi>and</hi> Shiftwell <hi>ſeverally, as in a Garden.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir. <hi>Ol.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>NO more of theſe coſtly feaſts nor go ſſipings.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Ha! Sir <hi>Oliver</hi> alone i'l ſtand here and liſſen.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir. <hi>Ol.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>No, no, I have a Plot to reaſſume my former an antient way of living.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift,</speaker>
                     <p>How will he leave us? O penurious curre!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Ol.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>I'l repoſe my truſt and Confidence in none but in my ſelf.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shif.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes i'l ſhare with thee villain and put a ſtop to all thy cunning.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[Sir <hi>Oliver</hi> pulls out a Letter.]</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Ol.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>This Letter does prepare the Phyſick I ſhortly intend to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter to <hi>Shiftwel</hi> and his Wife.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Does the plot lye there, then be attentive ears!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Ol.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>This Letter is an Imploration to regain my good wifes fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, with numberleſs proteſtations never ſo diſgracefully to live from her.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>More Knave thou, but for my own ends ile prevent thee.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Ol.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>But I looſe time,</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>— <hi>I muſt away,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>In Plots there is no danger like delay.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <stage>[Going out drops a Letter!]</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Damn'd Impoſture! but ile not rave nor rage but ſmoothly put a bar to his conſpiracy, and ſee he has left me further inſtructions to proceed, ile read it.</p>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:51398:15"/>
                     <stage>[Reads the Letter.]</stage>
                     <p>My Dear.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>PRethee pardon what I have done amiſs, and though I have been a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digal wanderer once more receive me home into thy favour: 'Tis but Juſtice in mee to be ſubmiſsive ſince I am ſo much guilty of ingratitude to the embraces of ſo kind a Wife. I proteſt religiouſly never to go back into that path of folly wherein I have been ſo long hedg'd, but poſt to come to thee, Embrace, Enjoy, Live, and never again to live apart from thee till death ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perates me from being</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thy endeared Husband Sir <hi>Oliver.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Very good now Ile go place my Engine, and quickly quench thy new deſires.</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>We both have laid our plots and his deſign,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Which he think's ſure's prevented thus by mine.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <head>Scen. Third.</head>
                  <stage>Moneylack <hi>Solus.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <p>HOw eaſy was I tempted to my ruine! I have a Neece ſaid he, now I know thou haſt a fair one two, whoſe amorus eyes have charm'd my heart and made me ſubject, to loves Deity! <hi>Maria!</hi> lovely <hi>Maria!</hi> to thy beauty I am a Captive and ever dedicate my ſelf to thy ſervice. How the ruſhing waves of love do tumble and beat upon my tender heart. My eyes are very dimne or almoſt out with gazing on the Sun whoſe light is coeleſtial, Me thinks I am in a dream.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>All things to nature contrary go.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I needs muſt ſleep and love commands it ſo!</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:51398:16"/>
                  <stage>[Sleeps and ſoft muſick playes and this Song.]
<lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>MUſes expreſſe in every line</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>A</hi> Phaenix <hi>vertues all divine!</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Richeſt of Nature in whoſe Eye</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>You Gods may ſee Divinity!</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>O what a charme in her does dwell</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>None but the Gods themſelves can tell?</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Her beams the Sun at Noon diſplayes,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Unable to extend his Rayes,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Did all but veiw her right they'd ſay,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>She is light and darkneſs Night and Day,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>O what a charm in her does dwell,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>None but the Gods themſelves can tell!</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </stage>
                  <stage>[He awakes]</stage>
                  <p>Ha! me thought I heard a heavenly voice ſinging in the praiſe of my <hi>Maria,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Bleſt be that voice, for ſhe is all divine!</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And I'm but mortal then ſhe can't be mine!</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Shiftwel.</stage>
                  <p>But I maſt ceaſe.</p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>My dear friend well met, have I not got a noble colour.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Faith I have been hard at it, but why ſo melancholly? thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lookeſt ill too, prithe the cauſe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>Truly I am ill, very ill and yet the cauſe—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>What iſt prithe tell me?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>He is my friend I cannot well deny him, 'tis love.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Love! in what kind</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>In the beſt kind, the worthieſt kind! A Cordial Honorable and Honeſt love.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Honeſt Love! Ha, ha, ha, Pox on ſuch love, and all the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:51398:16"/>Generation of it. Hang honeſt love, hate honeſt Women, ſtick to a Cup of good Sack and live as I do, and thou wilt never do amiſs ile warrant thee. Good <hi>Money lack</hi> go ſleep upon't, ſo good night, to morrow morn ile ſee you agen and hope to find you in another mood. Honeſtly in love, Ha, ha, ha!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But ere you go a word: why d' you pretend</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>You have a friendſhip when you ſlight your friend?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>By this ill temper all your love's deſtroy'd</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Neglect of kindneſs makes a kindneſs void,</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pardon what's paſt: permit me to implore</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Your love to think I lov'd you as before.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And though my humor uſhered out a jeſt,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>It was no ſpark of falſehood from my breaſt.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Declare your mind your pleaſure ile attend,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Damnation's due to him that fooles his Friend.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Then as I go the ſtory Ile relate</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>May heaven in all things make thee fortunate.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="scene">
                  <head>Scen. fourth.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Hairbrain <hi>and</hi> Swagger.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hair.</speaker>
                     <p>THis is the only life my brave <hi>Belſwagger.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Swag.</speaker>
                     <p>True, to ſpend a life muſing at home, Pox on ſuch ſottſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hair.</speaker>
                     <p>No, no thank my ſtars I have thought of better things.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Swag.</speaker>
                     <p>I but what ſhall we think of to get us a little more money, I have a great fancy to take a ramble to <hi>London,</hi> and your Fathers name wont gain us credit every where.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hair.</speaker>
                     <p>Not every where, but in ſome part of <hi>London</hi> ile engage it ſhall, but however being ſo nigh home Ile make a ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ep to him, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:51398:17"/>he may be orejoy'd to ſee me and prove liberal.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Swag.</speaker>
                     <p>Provided you'l ſtay at home and grow reformed.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hair.</speaker>
                     <p>Ile turn <hi>Puritan</hi> firſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Swag.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay I cant Imagine thou wilt leave mee</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hair.</speaker>
                     <p>No faith to leave thee in miſery would to my conſcience be</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>— <hi>a trouble without end,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Hee's no true Chriſtian, that proves falſe to his Frind.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Swag.</speaker>
                     <p>Enough I'me confident.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hair.</speaker>
                     <p>Well ile to my Father and return with all ſpeed poſſible, the mean time let no thoughts diſcontent thee, for as I have vowed</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Ile prove thy Friend and thou ſhalt ſee</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Ile find a plot to make the Miſer free.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="scene">
                  <head>Scen. Fifth.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Shiftwell.</stage>
                  <p>WEll little does <hi>Moneylack</hi> think <hi>Maria</hi>'s my Siſter, in the end he ſhall not doubt of his enterprize, I have left him in good hopes and am ſtoln to have the other tryal of my Amorous Dame, this is [<hi>knocks</hi> the door, and now good luck on my ſide.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Roger.</stage>
                  <p>Whoe's there.</p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>A friend.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                     <p>What is your Name.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>As you ſay that is to be thought on: I muſt pick-out ſome ſtrange name. <hi>Frank heart.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                     <p>O Sir cry your mercy I remember you and your ſuit and will be very ſerviceable to you, if now and then you will ſuffer me to be blithe and full of merry moods.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Roger</hi> where haſt been prithee?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:51398:17"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                     <p>At the ſpiget Sir is it not a very rainy day?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou art well waſh'd within I perceive, but <hi>Roger</hi> is your Lady at leiſure to diſcourſe, your Lady ſaid I ſee where ſhe comes!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Mrs <hi>Lovefree.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                     <p>Then 'tis time for me to be gone.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Roger.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs <hi>Love.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Ha! ſee where my Gallant is, I ſhall be courted certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and perhaps ſhall yeild.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Madam your humble ſervant; let your lilly white hand in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich my lips.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[Kiſſes her hand]</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs <hi>Love.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>You are very complemental Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Faith Madam I love you for millions of cauſes and you ſhall find it ſo if you p'eaſe introth dear Lady.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs <hi>Love.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Ile try him a little.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>And Ile try thee Ile hold thee a wager ere I have done with thee.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs <hi>Love.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>But Sir, you have been a very deboiſt Gentleman I hear.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>By what name pray Madam.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs <hi>Love.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Truly Sir my memory is none of the beſt I have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>So I believe: pray withall forget what you have heard and you ſhall hear no more of it, and upon that promiſe, come ſhall wee agree.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs <hi>Love.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>To what?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>To do as we would be done unto.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs <hi>Love.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>How's that.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>I could ſhew you Madam, with your good likeing.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs <hi>Love.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Some other time I preſume Sir will ſerve.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay no more Courtſhip if you love me Madam.</p>
                     <stage>Sings.</stage>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>O</hi> Cupid <hi>the Bow-man, I am not thy foe man,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>For I love this woman as well as</hi> I <hi>know man,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And therefore</hi> I <hi>pray thee with miſcheif to ſtay me,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And quickly to lay me in bed with this Lady.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:51398:18"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs <hi>Love.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>What call you this pray<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis my imploration Madam.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs <hi>Love.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>You are very fluent, 'tis meer flattery, they are moſt childiſh will beleive all that their Suitors ſay my moſt Poetical ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Moſt obdurate Lady, was ever widdow ſo hard to win, ſure her late Husband got not her Maiden-head ſhe is ſo backward.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs <hi>Love.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Adeiu Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Not yet ſweet Lady.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs <hi>Love.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Pray trouble me no more with your ſpeeches,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>O cruel reply to a Lovers ſuit!</p>
                     <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                     <p>how to diſſemble a little if ever you felt this paſſions pain, if ever you would pittied be your ſelf, or if you know that love has power to kill, commiſerate a heart ſo ſwel'd with love for you, that it will quickly break if you deny the juſtice of my requeſt, and if you are reſolv'd to remain Inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brable, I wiſh my Fortune yours, and if ever you love you may be ſerved ſo!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs <hi>Love.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>I am but a Woman and theſe words would move a ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid rock to pitty, Sir I can reſiſt no longer, your tongue has magick in't, you have overcome me and enjoy your Conqueſt. But firſt your Name.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Frankheart.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs <hi>Love.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>And mine <hi>Lovefree:</hi> then thou <hi>Frankheart</hi> takes mes <hi>Lovefree,</hi> without any farther Ceremony.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>A match, and one thing more Ile promiſe</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>My love to thee ſhall conſtant be and pure,</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs <hi>Love.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Let us to bed then and the bargains ſure.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>So this plot has hit right and</hi> I <hi>ſhall find,</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Riches enough to poiſe a troubled mind.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="scene">
                  <head>Scene the ſixth.</head>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:51398:18"/>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Shipton.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <p>NOw both in mind and form I am a perfect Witch, what hitherto I have done has ſpread my fame far wider then it is, ſo that thoſe who before looked upon me as a crack brain'd woman, now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to admire me, and eſteem my words as Oracles, eſpecially our Engliſh who only come to be reſolv'd of what I know will come to paſs of which here comes a great one.</p>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Abbot</hi> of <hi>Beverley.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>A B.</speaker>
                     <p>Reverend Matron whoſe all knowing skill our Country ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mires, part of which for my own intereſt I humbly come to crave.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ship.</speaker>
                     <p>Come near <hi>Abbot</hi> of <hi>Beverley,</hi> you are not ſo much diſguiſed but the Fox may be ſeen through the ſheeps skin.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>A. B.</speaker>
                     <p>She knowes me upon my life a witch!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ship.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis not thoſe Cloathes makes you a Lay perſon, no more then a long gown makes any man a Lawyer, pleaſe you to ſit you ſhall not go away unſatisfied of what you deſire.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>A. B.</speaker>
                     <p>I fear the downfall of our Abbies, but ere I know my doom, accept this ſacred Relique lately come from Rome, a ſure pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervative againſt all troubles and temptations.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ship.</speaker>
                     <p>O your Teſtimony is needleſs to the wiſe, of which I thus propheſie.</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>When the Cow does ride the Bull</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Then Prieſt beware thy skull!</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And when the lower ſhrubs do fall,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The great tree quickly follow ſhall.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The Mitred Peacoks lofty pride,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Shall to his maſter be a guide.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The poor ſhall grive to ſee that day</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And who did feaſt muſt faſt and pray.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Fate ſo decrees their overthrow,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Riches bring Pride and Pride brings woe?</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:51398:19"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>A. B.</speaker>
                     <p>This is omminous and touches State, thy inſolence muſt be corrected.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ship.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>There's none thats wiſe will ſay ſo</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>They that a Propheſie of me require</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Shalt know the Truth though not to their deſire</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Conſtrue it how you pleaſe, ſo</hi> I <hi>leave you.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>exit.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>A. B.</speaker>
                     <p>I fear ſhe does preſage too true, but ere I harbour ſuch a thought of my own downfall Ile cry <hi>vindicte</hi> on the witch that firſt induc'd mee too't.</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Then propheſing</hi> Shipton know</l>
                        <l>Beverleys <hi>great</hi> Abbot <hi>is thy Foe</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And does proteſt as he renounces ſin,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>To null thy witchcraft ere ſun ſet agen.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="act">
               <head>Act fourth.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>Scene the Firſt.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Abbot <hi>of</hi> Beverley <hi>and</hi> Beggars <hi>at one door, A Juſtice of peace</hi> Shipton <hi>and</hi> Radamon <hi>at the other.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>A. B.</speaker>
                     <p>BUt you muſt be ſure to ſwear point blanck.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Greg.</speaker>
                     <p>O through an inch bord Sir, lye and ſwear to it, 'tis the leaſt thing of an hundred, beſides what is it Beggars wont do for Money?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>A. B.</speaker>
                     <p>Very good but Mum, here comes the Juſtice and the witch.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Juſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Here our Officer has brought the party our warrant did command, Now ſay what you can aleadge againſt her and let her anſwer for her ſelf.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                     <p>Which ſhall be nothing</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Aſide</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>A. B.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſay Sir ſhe's a witch, and hope to prove it here by teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Juſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Well declare what can any of you teſtify againſt her.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Jug.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir an't pleaſe your Worſhip I have known her ever ſince
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:51398:19"/>ſhe was a Totterdas ſlut of fifteen, and ſhe alwaies threatned deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate things.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Juſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Piſh this is but talk, can any of you prove what you ſurmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for the ground of your warrant that ſhe is a witch?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                     <p>I now to the <hi>probat,</hi> ſpeak what you can.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Greg.</speaker>
                     <p>Ant pleaſe your worſhip I can ſafely take my corporal oath that ſhe is a —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[Snezes.]</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>A. B.</speaker>
                     <p>Out Ruſtick are you not aſhamed to ſneze in the Juſtices face?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
                     <p>Ant pleaſe your Worſhip I dare take my oath too that ſhe is a —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[ſnezes.]</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>A. B.</speaker>
                     <p>More impudence! this will ruine me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <hi>Jug.</hi> and <hi>Bab.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Ant pleaſe your good Worſhip to take our oathes, and we will confidently ſwear ſhe is a —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[ſnezes.]</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>A. B.</speaker>
                     <p>Diviliſh conſpiracy! an Oath ſticks in each throat and none can gulp it out.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Juſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Pray Sir what was your meaning to bring theſe Mechanicks here to deride me?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>A. B.</speaker>
                     <p>No Sir but—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Juſt.</speaker>
                     <p>But what? know Sir I take it for an affront put upon me, for which theſe your Teſtimonials ſhall all find ſevere puniſhment thus to upbraid juſtice, but firſt ſay woman are you guilty of what they accuſe you off or no?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ship.</speaker>
                     <p>No right worſhipful Sir, and here I do defie what all of them out of malice have moſt diſgracefully termed me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Juſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Once more ſpeak you, or any, or all of you, can you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict her, can you prove her a Witch?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes an't pleaſe we can all ſwear ſhe is a</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[ſneze.]</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Juſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Out impudent Cattel: Clark drive them in, and then make each perſons <hi>Min<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>mus</hi> to the County Goal, to anſwer to two In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictments. The one for upbraiding and derideing mee a Juſtice of Peace in <hi>Goram,</hi> the other for faſly accuſing Mother <hi>Shipton</hi> a woeman of good repute and converſation.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>A. B.</speaker>
                     <p>O I am undone! pray Sir be merciful.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Juſt.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Reprobates away.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I ſhall be more ſevere to you if you ſtay.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exeunt,</hi> A Beverley. Beggars, <hi>and</hi> Clark.</stage>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:51398:20"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>A thouſand thanks to your worſhip for being juſt to inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Juſt.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis thy deſert farewel.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Juſtice.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                     <p>Now have I not plaid a true Lovers part<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ship.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou haſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                     <p>Fear not theſe by blows</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Dread not to meddle with concerns of State,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Guarded by Fins thou needſt not fear thy Fate.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exeunt</hi> with horrid Muſick.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>Scene ſecond.</head>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Shiftwel</hi> Solus.</stage>
                  <p>I'm ſorry and yet I cannot chooſe to laugh at my poor friend <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neylacks</hi> misfortune: he loves, he loves honeſty, nay my Siſter too, and yet I blame him: O that men in this world ſhould be wrapt up in ſuch dotage and ſtupidity to what end? where is their aime? would any man be an Epicure? can he boaſt himſelf ſo without the ſenſe of variety! would he be a Phyloſopher? can he imagine to find the ſtone by beating on one experiment? would he be a Schollar and never turn over a new leaf: O ignorance inexpreſsible! of which I thank my ſtars I am but little guilty off: the beſt of knowledge is experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. A man may gueſs at many things, but when he has found them experimentally he is confident, ſo ſay I, I thought my new provided widdow was much inriched, and now I have found it true, nay my pocket does pronounce 'tis verity it ſelf.</p>
                  <stage>[ſhakes his pockets.]</stage>
                  <p>And now having got a ſecond to my Knight, I hope I ſhall croſs the Proverb <hi>And between two ſtooles ſit ſure:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The next plot,</hi> Moneylack's <hi>contrived for thee!</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Then thou muſt play the cunning man for me.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Old crafty</hi> Whore-hound <hi>look well to thy hits</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>When friends are faulty</hi> Shiftwel <hi>finds his witts.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <head>Scene third.</head>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:51398:20"/>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Hairbraine</hi> Solus.</stage>
                  <p>VVEll was ever Heart ſo juſt with Avarice as is the old dotard my Father, who at the approaching of winter muſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dauntedly expect to kick up his heels, and yet to want the charity of croſsing my hand with one ſmall mite of Silver, this is cold comfort to carry to my friend, and yet I muſt return to him: but now I think on't Father ſince thou art ſo unkind to give me nothing, ile be ſo civil to find a means to know when I ſhall have all, i'me Heir though a wild one: hereabouts lives the good old Mother <hi>Shipton,</hi> ſhe's wiſe they ſay and can preſage prittily: this is the door ſure ile knock.</p>
                  <stage>(knocks.)</stage>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Abigal. Shiptons</hi> Maid.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Abi.</speaker>
                     <p>Your buſineſs Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hair.</speaker>
                     <p>Sweetheart is the good Mother <hi>Shipton</hi> within.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Abi.</speaker>
                     <p>But not at leiſure as yet, you impart the occaſion of your coming to me Sir, I am her ſecret ſervant.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hair.</speaker>
                     <p>Why then prithe doſt know Sir <hi>Habbakuk Holdfaſt</hi> of this County.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Abi.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes an antient Gentleman, much diſeaſed and lives nere <hi>Pomfret.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hair.</speaker>
                     <p>The very ſame.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Abi.</speaker>
                     <p>And what of him?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hair.</speaker>
                     <p>Why prithe ask thy Miſtreſs how long ſhe thinks 'tis poſſible for him to live.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Abi.</speaker>
                     <p>See where ſhe comes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Shipton.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ship.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir I know the party you enqui e off, and concerning whom I thus Propheſie.</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The Grave provided has a room</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>For his old age: His hour is come.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>So I leave you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit <hi>Shipton.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:51398:21"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hair.</speaker>
                     <p>So ſweet heart thank thy Miſtreſs.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Abi.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay but pray Sir ſtay, if you forget to open your purſe, I ſhan't forget to open my mouth: do you think I can live with thanks? the Belly requires meat, and the back cloathing, thank you quoth he, marry come up.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hair.</speaker>
                     <p>Prithee be not ſo hot, there's for thee.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Abi.</speaker>
                     <p>Well I hope thanks will ſuffice you Sir, though it would not me, ſo farewell Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Abigal.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hair.</speaker>
                     <p>Fleſh I have given her half my ſtock, I am poor and yet if I have nere ſo little I can't forbear to be liberal: well Gentillity ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced with Poverty is the worſt accompliſhment a Gallant of this Age, can be inveſted with: but to the repetition of the Propheſie.</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The Grave provided has a Room,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>For his old Age, his hour is come.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>Heaven ſend the time: now with a heart fraughted with joy.</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Ile to my</hi> Swagger <hi>and to him expreſs,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The election of my future happineſs.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="scene">
                  <head>Scen fourth.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Shiftwell <hi>and</hi> Moneylack.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift</speaker>
                     <p>FAith her diſpoſition is moſt ſtrange.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>'Twas eaſier for to ſpurn the Cyclops Anvil down, and kick it into Attomes in the Air then to obtain her love.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>O think not ſo.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>Have I not cauſe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>At laſt after a conſtant and heard purſuit ſhe may be wone.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>Could I but hope ſo much, did all the Stars malignant Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences threaten Fate oppoſite to my happineſs, I would not deem them worthy of my obſervation, but perſevere till I obtained or fell.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Conjecture ſtill the beſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:51398:21"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis eaſier to advice then to perform.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>In theſe times young Ladies for a while do mantle their affection in diſlike, let not an ignorance of Virgins wills diſturbe thy breaſt with weak diſpair.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Maria <hi>and her maide alone.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>See and exalt your eyes to happineſs.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Maria</hi> and her Maid, I ſee a Lute: let us eſcape the light and it is likely we ſhall hear her ſing.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maria.</speaker>
                     <p>Now give it me, is it in tune?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maid.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes Madam.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>Forbear a while to play upon the ſpheers ye ſervants to the Deities, the Gods will blame you if you keep the air of her all ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhing Harmony from their ears.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[<hi>Maria</hi> ſings this ſong.]
<lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>O ſweet</hi> Diana <hi>vertuous Queen</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>That doſt affect the meadows green!</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>By heavens edict the guide of night</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And doſt in freſh leave's woods delight!</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Like to the Nymphs ſo ſuffer mee</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>To conſeerate my ſelf to thee.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Thou that for luſt didſt transform</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Acteon <hi>to a Hart ſo charm</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>With vertuous ſpels each Virgins heart</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>That men may never them divert</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>From purity: or elſe pray make</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Them other hearts for Virgins ſake.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Maria <hi>and her Maid.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>Now have you heard her reſolution.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>That ſhe diſguizes, not her love you mean.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>True and I am moſt miſerable!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>But ſee here ſhe's all alone: now ſpeak to her Ile withdraw and pray for your ſucceſs.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>Thanks good friend: hail Natures moſt perfect work, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="38" facs="tcp:51398:22"/>continual Idea of my admyring Soul! however your poor Adorer Lady with a gracious look of your beloved eyes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>Alas your ſmile Sir is in vain, for in ſhort, if you'l give me leave, I call to witneſs every particular inſtance, and tends to any Chriſtians happineſs, that I will never enter into Marriage: and for your ſaying you muſt dye for me, I hold it but a common comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of idle Lovers, and therefore wiſh you ſo much happineſs to live without me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>O be not ſo unmerciful! had your Mother faireſt Lady, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exorable been, you had not been, nor thoſe crimſon Roſes ever ſpread upon your lovely cheeks: has Nature liberally heaped the raireſt perfections ſhe could give Mortality to no end? ſurely no; as you are a daughter of a beautious Mother, ſhe being dead, you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich the world unto you by your iſſue. Be not ſo cruel then, my fair <hi>Maria,</hi> let not your tongue degenerate from your form.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir you have heard me ſpeak what I intend.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>Be not a Tygreſs Lady.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir I muſt leave you, and leave you this humour, I reſpect you as you are a Gentleman of my acquaintance, but if any more you trouble me with your Court ſhip I ſhall utterly have you: ſo farewell.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Maria.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>Does a fair face preſage a cruel heart! Nature is grown de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crepit ſure, and all things ſublunary erre againſt her rule of order.</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>This is my fate, the fates</hi> I <hi>can't prevent.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And till the end</hi> I <hi>know not their intent.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>What is ſhe ſtill obdurate?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>Beyond expreſsion!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Yet let not theſe doubt puzzle you, you will be happy, and enjoy her, I am confident you will: this is a common cuſtome in young hearts.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>But this is a fixed Star.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Fixed in your heart it ſeems, but otherwiſe I doubt it, herefore in the end doubt not you of your deſire.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>You have ſtirred a feeble releif within me, friend that my dear <hi>Maria</hi> may be warm and I will nouriſh it to ſome height,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>A neceſsa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>y none muſt want which do</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſire fruition of thoſe whom they woe.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="scene">
                  <head>Scen. Fifth.</head>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:51398:22"/>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Captain, Priſcilla, <hi>and Mother</hi> Prue.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Priſ.</speaker>
                     <p>CAptain you promiſed me a new Gown and have broke your word I deſire therefore to be acquitted your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
                     <p>Pretty <hi>Priſ.</hi> my Tennants are ſlow in paying their Rents I had not failed thee elſe, but thou art very fine as you are.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Priſ.</speaker>
                     <p>That's without thanks to you, 'tis no coſt of yours: I am be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding to a better friend for't.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pru.</speaker>
                     <p>But in truth Captain you muſt become more liberal to my Daughter for the future.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Priſ.</speaker>
                     <p>What do you think Ile venture my reputation for your Oaths, flattering words and a little fooliſh pleaſure?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pru.</speaker>
                     <p>No indeed ſhe muſt be maintained with other Materials: If ſhe goes not fine and gallant, ſhe muſt bid farewell for ever to all hollidayes: the Honorable and right Worſhipful will not care for her embraces then.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
                     <p>Are you againſt me too Mother? I thought you had had a greater kindneſs for me then ſo.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pru.</speaker>
                     <p>Indeed Captain you know I have much reſpected you: but you muſt think of providing better for my Girl.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cap. Priſ.</speaker>
                     <p>I love thee, give me thy hand, and though I never made uſe of my Credit in that kind, ile vow before my Mother ile take thee up a new Gown to morrow,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Priſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Perform't and then you ſee <hi>Priſcilla</hi> wi'l requite your kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
                     <p>Then wee are agreed, ile do it, now will I joak with my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Bawd a little. My wonderful old Mother methinks you are grown merry of the ſuddain, well is there any wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in <hi>Europe</hi> that can remember the building of the Capitol, I dare pronounce tis you: would I had as much mony as you have ſpent in Almanacks ſince you could make uſe of them, I ſhould be as rich as the grand Govenour of a province.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pru.</speaker>
                     <p>Well well Captain though you make a mock of my age, you would be glad to live ſo long your ſelf.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:51398:23"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Priſ.</speaker>
                     <p>There is but ſmall hopes to imagine hee'l ever arrive to that Antiquity, his debauchneſs will ſhorten his daies, beſides he's ſo quarrelſome I wonder he has liv'd till now.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
                     <p>Piſh you prate, but is ſupper ready Mother.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pru.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes but we muſt ſtay for Eſquire <hi>Hairbrain.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
                     <p>Will he be here?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pru.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, and his friend Mr, <hi>Swagger.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Hairbrain <hi>and</hi> Swagger</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Priſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Long look't for comes at laſt, Mr. <hi>Hairbrain</hi> your welcome</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hair.</speaker>
                     <p>Thanks my dear <hi>Priſ.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pru.</speaker>
                     <p>Mr.<hi>Swaggar</hi> you are welcome too.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hair.</speaker>
                     <p>Mother your daughter lookes exceeding well methinks.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pru.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Venus</hi> be praiſed ſhe needs no art of painting, her face al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes wears its native colours.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Priſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Paint out upon't, I ſhould be loath to dawb my face with oyntment.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
                     <p>But many of as good features, have not ſo nice a ſtomack.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Priſ.</speaker>
                     <p>I credit you, and have heard many raile againſt it as if they ſcorn'd to adulterate their faces.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
                     <p>You women no diſſemblers are, but he that can live without you is a happy man.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hair.</speaker>
                     <p>But we trifle time, Mother lead way wee'l follow come <hi>Swag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> within wee ſhall find a Miſtreſs for thee.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Priſ.</speaker>
                     <p>My Mother has a ſcore or two at your ſervice.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Swag.</speaker>
                     <p>Thanks my fair <hi>Priſcilla.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exeunt</hi> Hairbrain Swagger <hi>and</hi> Pris <hi>and</hi> Prue.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
                     <p>Well I muſt expect little enjoyment of dear <hi>Priſ.</hi> while <hi>Hair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brain's</hi> here, would I could win her affection to my ſelf I would carry her far enough out of all their reaches. She is <hi>Proxrots</hi> only child and ſhe's rich.</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>She may turne honeſt after ſhe's a wife.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>However money makes a happy life.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <trailer>Finis Actus Quarti.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="act">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:51398:23"/>
               <head>Act fifth,</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>Scen firſt,</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Shiftwell <hi>with a Letter in his hand.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <p>SEe this Letter will eaſe the heat of my troubled friend, and with more ſpirit make him enact what I muſt deſire him to perform to the life: 'Tis now high time to place my Engine, and indeed to work it, Sir <hi>Oliver</hi> keeps cloſe to his ſtudy — <hi>'tis to no good intent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And I muſt watch his cunning to prevent</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Ile ſtrait to <hi>Moneylack</hi> and put my deſign in execution.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Moneylack.</stage>
                  <p>But ſee ye how fortunately he comes, my dear friend read that and then judge of my prevalency with <hi>Maria.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <stage>Opens and reads the Letter.</stage>
                  <p>Sir having received a perticular account of your worth and quality I am ſorry I have ſo long repaid your affection to me with diſdain. I would not have you triumph that I have ſo recollected my ſelf, nor yet deſpair in any thing to the contrary, for at preſent I can only ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie you that I eſteem you as an accompliſhed Gentleman.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Maria.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Is this her own hand.</p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Is this mine? I am ſorry you gueſs my friendſhips to be flattery.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>No more, I credit you, and by this means inſpired a ſecond breath into a heartleſs Lover, 'tis beyond the reach of Oratory to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare thy gratitude. Nay the well wiſhes of your friend have the ſame power to implore the like ſucceſs in all your own concerns.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>You are very bountiful, but now I muſt make bold to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy you in a buſineſs wherein if you fail to be either ſecret or dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent 'twill be my utter ruine.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>Then if I be may the deſtruction fall upon my head, declare.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>This it is, when the goſſiping was, after dinner ſteping into the garden I eſpyed Sir <hi>Oliver</hi> murmuring to himſelf, and thinking it to be no goodneſs; ſquatted under a buſh and heard the Rogues de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, very ſpeedily of leaving my wife and returning to his own and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:51398:24"/>with her to remain till death them depart, after he was gone I found <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Letter (which he had dropt) which was to be ſent to his wife with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> great imploration for pardon for former errours, &amp; proteſtations of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ire love upon a favourable acceptance. Now to put an obſtacle to his intent, I would have you in a Serjeants habit, go and arreſt him at my ſuit upon two actions, one of Treſpaſs, and the other of Battery, (for I'm ſure he hath battered my wife) then threaten to carry him to the Counter, and in the <hi>interim</hi> ile come and make up the buſineſs; and aſſure thee <hi>Maria</hi> in the bargain. Time and place to meet with him you ſhall receive in a note from me this even.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>Then if I fail to do it to the life call me Hypocrite.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Enough, farewell for the preſent.</p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>exit</hi> Moneylack.</stage>
                     <p>Now for my widdow.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>exit.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>Scene ſecond.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>The Scene draws,</hi> Swagger <hi>making a paſs at</hi> Hairbrain, Hairbrain <hi>having his eye fixed on a letter, the Captain keeping of</hi> Swagger, Priſcilla, <hi>two other whores and Mother</hi> Prue.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Swag.</speaker>
                     <p>REfuſe my Miſtriſs health, 'tis a crime which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but his death ſhall expiate have I been ever his continual friend, and am I ſlighted thus, ile raiſe all the dreadful furies from the infernal ſhades to ſtigmatize him full of my revenge.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pru.</speaker>
                     <p>Come, come, Ile have no quarrels in my houſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hair.</speaker>
                     <p>Mum Impudence! Ile meet his fury.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Swag.</speaker>
                     <p>How now Hag, can you hinder quarrels in a Bawdy-houſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
                     <p>If you can, you have more power then a Conſtable, but let my entreaties beg a reconcilement.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Swag.</speaker>
                     <p>They are in vain and do but exaſperate the proſecution of my juſt revenge advance Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hair.</speaker>
                     <p>Stay beaſt unworthy of the name of man, much leſs unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy thy of the name of Friend, firſt peruſe this letter and then I ſhall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay the ſeeming confidence you have in your own valour.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Gives</hi> Swagger <hi>the Letter.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <p>Of what moment is extravagancy, or to what end ſerves a riotus life, ſeeing both the one and the other are ſubject to viciſſitude and ready to yeild at the leaſt puffe of winde that blowes from a conatry ſhore! O my diſobedience! To forſake the intern love of a Parent
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:51398:24"/>for the fruition of thy laſcivious company! where is my fathers gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en Crop, I ſhould have reaped? given to my Uncle whoſe love is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> cold to me as death it ſelf. Now hell hound doſt thou ſec unto what diſtreſs by thy alluſions I am now driven too, read there how my mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery is characted; revenge is ſweet. Advance therefore for I am re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to ſend thy baſe polluted ſoul into the flames of <hi>Phlegeton.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Priſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay <hi>Hairbrain</hi> prithee let me perſwade thee.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2. <hi>W.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>And <hi>Swagger</hi> let me perſwade thee.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. And Gentlemen pray let me perſwade you both.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Priſ.</speaker>
                     <p>I expected a more familiar way of ſcuffling then this.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2. W.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I thought each man with his mate would fight</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Battails not full of danger but delight.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>3. W.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Soft kiſſes, ſweet embraces, and ſuch ſport</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>As often's uſed in the Venerial Court.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hair.</speaker>
                     <p>Out Whores trouble me not.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
                     <p>Methinks I find a ſudden alteration within me, affection tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> even now was ſo powerful, is of the ſudden turn'd to utter hate, and my heart for bringing forth any fruits of love to <hi>Priſcilla</hi> is as barren a</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The ſand that lies on the ſea ſhore.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>I will embrace that love that hates a whore.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pru.</speaker>
                     <p>Well Gentlemen if you are ſo mute or mad I know not which nor I don't care whether, wee'l be ſo civil to leave you, my Ladie will find other Gallants to be more gently embraced by, ſo farewel ha, ha, ha.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Pru. <hi>and all the whores laughing.</hi> Manent <hi>Ha. Swag</hi> and <hi>Cap.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Swag.</speaker>
                     <p>Now Sir here take my ſword and make a paſſage for my ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> that it may leave ſo vile a habitation as this body.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hair.</speaker>
                     <p>No here take mine and do me that courteſie,</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>— <hi>For length of life to me,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Is but the product of more mirſery.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
                     <p>Pray Gentlemen without being thought too rude, may I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to know the cauſe of your Agrieveance.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Swag.</speaker>
                     <p>Then know Sir, to this Gentleman my friend bey on expreſsion</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>— I <hi>have been too rude,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>I'm guilty of the ſin ingratitude.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>By my perſwaſions to lead an Extravagant life, he has lately lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> a fair eſtate, and on his fathers death bed merited his curſes: fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> which I thus fall his ſacrifice.</p>
                     <stage>offers to fall on his ſword</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hair.</speaker>
                     <p>For heaven ſake forbear: ſo much a freſh is my love kindle
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:51398:25"/>that I have both forgotten nay and forgiven all, your confeſſion to me, ſince all is paſt recovery, is a ſufficient ſatisfaction.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Swag.</speaker>
                     <p>Is this not pollicy to delay my death?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hair.</speaker>
                     <p>By all thats good it is not if you dare credit me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Swag.</speaker>
                     <p>You may be confident I will.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hair.</speaker>
                     <p>Then let all paſs, we muſt now joyn prudence to our pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and by a ſerious life regain the loſs of vertue.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Swag.</speaker>
                     <p>With a heart as full of holy ardencie as thoſe that devoutly implore zealous mercies from their Saints, or as votaries from their Goddeſſes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
                     <p>Pray may a third man intervene that has not over vertuouſly inclin'd himſelf &amp; make a joynt reſolution with you for repentance.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <hi>Hair,</hi> and <hi>Swag.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>With all our hearts, but what is this.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Deſpair.
<l>
                        <hi>I am</hi> Deſpair <hi>and come to tell you, late</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Repentance nere can make you fortunate:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Of all your pleaſures take a ſecond view,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And let</hi> Deſpair <hi>your comfort be: adeiu.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </stage>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hair.</speaker>
                     <p>Hell take <hi>Deſpair</hi> it ſhall never enter into my breaſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Swag.</speaker>
                     <p>Nor mine.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
                     <p>Nor mine but ſee another apparition!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Hope.
<l>
                        <hi>I am that vertue which does underprop</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The fainting heart of man with comfort: Hope</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And to you diſcontented now appear</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To bid you ſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ght</hi> Deſpair <hi>and not to fear,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That if you do confide: your Hope will be</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The anchor of your true Fidelity.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </stage>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
                     <p>Hope thee I embrace, and friends let joyn hand and hearts in the height of ſorrow to have the greateſt Hope, by ſome learned Authors</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>— <hi>Wee'l take advice</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>To embrace all vertue, and avoid all vice.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <head>Scen third:</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Shipton.</stage>
                  <p>NOw am I experienced in the Magical Sciences, as much as ever was the fam'd <hi>Medea</hi> or <hi>Circe.</hi> whoſe cuning has left a wonder to the world, ſo ſhall <hi>Shiptons</hi> too! but to what end? what will the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:51398:25"/>applauſive clamour of the world benefit me, when endles torments are my only comfort. But why do I ſuffer this conſideration? ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> not my deeds merited the fruit of Hell? but how? Is it a ſin to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet riches when one ſuffers the contempt of the world by reaſon of poverty? yes coveting ambitiouſly is execrable, but having a heart o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to embrace the deluſions of the Devil, that, that alore is damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble! then deteſtable <hi>Shipton</hi> look into the glaſs of thy infirmities, which are ſo many they almoſt work a deſpair in me to cry <hi>peccavi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> yet have we not powers above that, over hels prevalency are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominant? then will I cleave to them! but is it not too late? ſooner I confeſs would have been better! but ſurely a heart penitentially incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned is not contemptible! then Devil look to thy ſelf, thou thinkeſt I am thine, but thou ſhalt find ere long thou art deceived. From thee</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And all thy Helliſh Sciences I now regret,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Heaven will forgive if Hell I doe forget.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <stage>Exit</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="scene">
                  <head>Scen fourth.</head>
                  <stage>Enter Radamon.</stage>
                  <p>HA, ha, ha, how I laugh at a poor crew of ſimple ſinners who perſue temptation more then it does them: who will ſcruple to ſwear dam me, ſince 'tis Allamode? and who will avoide living vitiouſly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable in this world though they purchaſe Hell in the next? witneſs poor <hi>Shipton</hi> whoſe Name ecchoes out admiration, to whom I have been a ſmall attendant, but for no ſmal wages, I ſerve for ſouls but here ſhe comes.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Shipton.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ship.</speaker>
                     <p>Ha! heres my ſoul catcher! now all goodneſs be my aſſiſtance we'ome my <hi>Radamon,</hi> thou art come juſt in the nick to accompliſh an earneſt requeſt I have too thee?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                     <p>Name it and 'tis granted.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ship.</speaker>
                     <p>Do't and ile confirm thou art a miraculous Devil! by all the Helliſh conſpiracy thou ere waſt maſter of, I do conjure thee to empty the Sea and make me ſole commandreſs of all the riches therein lye ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panded!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:51398:26"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                     <p>Impudent Witch! what has in joyn'd thee to that arrogancy to deſire that which all the power Hell could ever boaſt off never was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble yet to grant.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ship.</speaker>
                     <p>So his nonperformance of</p>
                     <stage>Aſide</stage>
                     <p>This ſhall be my plea: why <hi>Radamon</hi> go to the ſumme of our contract art thou not my ſervant.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes I have been but now come in my Maſters name to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand thy ſoul.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ship.</speaker>
                     <p>My ſoul, ha, ha, ha!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes thy Soul witch doſt laugh.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ship.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes &amp; does defie thee, know vaunting Devil by hells inſtigation I have hitherto lead a vitious life I have now found out the way to vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, which to follow I am ſo undeterminably inclin'd, that no tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſhall withdraw me from the perſeverance of ſo good a reſolution.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                     <p>Conceited woman how doſt thou flatter thy ſelf with impoſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities: conſider thy innumerable frailties, conſider thy daily practiſe of Murder, Witchcraft, fatal Propheſies and what not that has meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted hells endleſs torments: conſider theſe rightly, and thou wilt find they are ſo pondrous they will weigh down the thoughts of any true felicity.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ship.</speaker>
                     <p>Delude me no more, begon and tell thy Maſter, <hi>Shipton</hi> walks in a path will make her truly happy by avoiding Hell.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou lyeſt, thou art mine, reſign thy ſelf to me and that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently or ile raiſe hels fiery King himſelf withall his dreadful furies to drag thee to his ever burning pallace!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ship.</speaker>
                     <p>Do, I dread them not.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Junx elke tu tenon Emon potidoma on Andra.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[Pluto <hi>with other devils with rakes</hi> enters]</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Plu.</speaker>
                     <p>The cauſe of this great help thou craves?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                     <p>See where ſhe ſtands with ſuch audacity Hell cannot ſhew the like precedent.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Plu.</speaker>
                     <p>Have you expreſt our commands.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes and ſhe ſcorns them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Plu.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Shipton</hi> thou art mine.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ship.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes and you can take me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Plu.</speaker>
                     <p>Seize on her ſtraight.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[The Devils poke with their rakes and cannot touch her]</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Plu.</speaker>
                     <p>What are you grown feeble? ile joyn my ſtrength!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:51398:26"/>
                  <stage>[All cannot touch her.]</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Plu.</speaker>
                     <p>What preſervative has ſhe got againſt our power?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                     <p>Too ſure ſhe is ſheilded by thoſe powers above, to which ours is impotent!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Plu.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>We muſt uſe other means</hi> Shipton <hi>farewell,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Pluto <hi>ſtill hopes to ſee thee hang in Hell.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> all Devils with horrid muſick.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ship.</speaker>
                     <p>I muſt now then conclude this to be the laſt attempt, ſtill, ſtill, protect me ye</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>— <hi>Powers Coeleſtial and ile impart,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Your glorious Mercy with a thankful heart.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Shipton.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="scene">
                  <head>Scen. Fifth.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Sir Oliver <hi>and his man</hi> David.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Ol.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Now <hi>David</hi> how thinkeſt thou of my cunning.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dav.</speaker>
                     <p>Very well truly Sir, you have a brain ile, ſay that for you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Ol.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Poor <hi>Shiftwel</hi> it troubles me though. O me what a brave man he was, no meeting at the Horſe race, Cocking, Hunting, Shooting or Fowling at which <hi>Shiftwel</hi> was not a principal Gameſter, and compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion for the Nobility.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                     <p>I Sir he has paid deer for thoſe follies, and 'tis but juſtice that ſuch as ſoar above their pitch, and will not be warn'd by his example ſhould like him ſhare in the miſeries that wait upon it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Ol.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Thou ſayeſt right <hi>David,</hi> and I in pitty have for theſe few years lent him a helping hand to raiſe his fortunes, but now for my own ſelf intereſt ſake I muſt leave him, therefore <hi>David</hi> run and fetch my boots and bring them to the Inne, ile haſte before.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                     <p>I am gone Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> David.</stage>
                  <stage>[<hi>Sir</hi> Oliver <hi>goes off. and comes on agen preſently.</hi>]</stage>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:51398:27"/>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Love free <hi>looking out at her Belcony.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. <hi>Lovefree.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Bleſs me, ſure that is my old Knight that creeps a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long ſo or my eye-ſight failes me!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Money lack <hi>in a Serjeants habit.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>I arreſt you Sir, by the name of Sir <hi>Oliver Whorehound.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. <hi>Love.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Ha! 'tis he and arreſted. I muſt down and know the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent.</p>
                     <stage>[deſcends and ſtands within the Arras.]</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Ol.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Arreſt me Sir at whoſe ſuit?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>At Mr. <hi>Shiftwells</hi> ſuit upon two actions, with two or three ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutions which ſhall grinde you to powder when I have you in the Counter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Ol.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>At Mr. <hi>Shiftwells</hi> ſuite, thou doſt belye him Varlet, he I dare lay will weep when he heres on't.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes like a Milſtone.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Shiftwel.</stage>
                  <p>See where he comes you had beſt tell him ſo.</p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Ol.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Nephew <hi>Shiftwel</hi> you are come moſt opportunely to free me from this <hi>Band<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>g.</hi> I know you gave no way to it nor had you any reaſon ſo to do.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Bleſs me who do I ſee; <hi>Shiftwell</hi> is thy Name? O deceitful man!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Are you a Serjeant acquainted with the danger of a reſcue, yet ſtand here prating in the open ſtreets, the Counters ſure a ſafer place to parley in.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Ol.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Your reaſon for this diſgrace to me?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis but juſtice in me. The reaſon you ſhall know hereafter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Ol.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Pray here me ſpeak.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Whilſt I like the adder ſtop my ears, or did I liſten, though you ſpake with the tongue of Angels I am not to be altered.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Ol.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Pray make me ſenſible of the offence I have done, if it be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and I will make the beſt of my eſtate to end the difference.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. <hi>Love.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>How does my heart now pant bewteen Hope and fear, to know the period of this buſineſs,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>He ſhew you ſome mercy which is this. That I will not tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ure you with falſe hopes, but make you know what you ſhall truſt
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:51398:27"/>too: I have ſeiz'd upon your eſtate already, yet that ſhall not ſuff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> therefore Serjeant do your duty: yet ſtay Sir <hi>Oliver,</hi> I have conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to propoſe, upon which Ile free you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> David.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir I have been at the Inne and finding you not there came back to look you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Ol.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>My journies ſtopt now <hi>David,</hi> Mr <hi>Shiftwell</hi> you may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe but I imagine the next Tavern, or ſome other place might be more convenient.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>With all my heart lets to the next Tavern, go ſend for two or three friends and diſcourſe of it there at large.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit Sir</hi> Ol. Mo. <hi>and</hi> Shift.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                     <p>Ha! a Serjeant on my maſters back, <hi>Shiftwel</hi> has napt him, now all will out as ile go hear.</p>
                     <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs <hi>Love.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Now is my ſhame as evident as day light, O unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate woman! that I ſhould have the ill-luck above all other men to meet with him, that I fear I ſhall find more then an honeſt man: but come what will, I muſt follow and in my Knights cauſe outlook the world with confidence.</p>
                     <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>The Scene a Tavern.</stage>
                  <stage>Sir <hi>Oliver. Shiftwel. Moneylack David</hi> and a <hi>Scrivener, Shiftwelis</hi> wife <hi>Maria</hi> and Sir <hi>Olivers</hi> wife apart as in another room.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shifs.</speaker>
                     <p>Now Scrievener read the propoſitions.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Scriev.</speaker>
                     <p>That for the injury deſigned to Mr. <hi>Shiftwell</hi> you will free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly give him a hundred pounds yearly during his life, and after his deceaſe to Maria.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>Ha! to <hi>Maria,</hi> I can't conceive the reaſon, but ile be ſilenced till the future.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Scriev.</speaker>
                     <p>Secondly to make Mr. <hi>Shiftwels</hi> wife joynture a hundred pounds <hi>per annum</hi> more during her life, and laſtly to keep his wife and familie twelve years, and if at the twelve years end you intend to leave them fairly to give a quarters warning.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>(<hi>Sir</hi> Olivers <hi>wife ſteps out</hi>)</stage>
                  <p>Heres one ſaies no to that but the reſt for your freedome Sir <hi>Oliver</hi> I muſt conſent too.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> her ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>k and ſcarf</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:51398:28"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Oliver.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Ha! my dear wife.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Ol. W.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>You have been a hopeful husband, but blame me not if I have paid you in your coyn.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>I am amazed.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Ol. W.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Nay ſtare not Mr <hi>Frankfort</hi> that was pretended, you and I have been a little better acquainted, but not with a thought that your wife and my husband were ſuch ſure bedfellowes</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Ol.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Well then wife I hope you'l pardon me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Ol. W.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>I do and expect the ſame from you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Well I have loſt a good generous cuſtomer by the bargain, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> be contented, but Sir <hi>Oliver</hi> you freely ſeal to theſe articles the laſt only omitted by your wives in junction.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Ol.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Withall my heart, upon the giving me a bond for redelive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of my eſtate.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>That I will, only one thing more remayns: that upon <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria's</hi> acceptance of the perſon ſhe affects for her husband, you will pay down the marriage portion in your hands remaining.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Ol.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Moſt freely.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Then pray witneſſe the ſealing and delivery.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>They ſeal and deliver.</stage>
                  <p>Now Sir <hi>Oliver</hi> what were have done we can't undoe, therefore Mr. <hi>Moneylace:</hi> diſcover your ſelf and accept my Siſter <hi>Maria</hi> for your wife.</p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                     <p>And I accept him as my only happineſs.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>Deareſt Lady you have raiſed me to a joy beyond my thoughts may heaven requite you for your kindneſs, and I wear out my life to do you ſervice.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Ol.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Bleſs me here are wonders in ridles.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir <hi>Oliver</hi> I muſt crave your pardon for my rudeneſs.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>There is a general pardon granted, and now good wife lets ſee how our ends will meet agen.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sh. W.</speaker>
                     <p>I accept thee freely.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Then we are all friends.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:51398:28"/>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Serjeant.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                     <p>I arreſt you Sir.</p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>arreſts</hi> Shiftwel.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>Arreſt him Villain?</p>
                     <stage>offers to draw.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
                     <p>Pray Brother with bold a little, at whoſe ſuit?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Mr <hi>Scrape.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <p>At this Gentlemans.</p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>Then Ile end all. My noble Uncle!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Scra.</speaker>
                     <p>I have a requeſt to take my ſecurity for this Gentlemans debt, he is become my brother.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Scra.</speaker>
                     <p>Your Brother?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>Even ſo ſir, to morrow I'm to marry this Gentlewoman his ſiſter: releaſe him therefore pray ſir for your nephews ſake.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Scra.</speaker>
                     <p>That I will Serjeant be gone I have ſatisfied you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Serjeant.</stage>
                  <p>And pray Gentlemen pardon my ignorance of all theſe proceedings and Nephew I wiſh you much happineſs.</p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <p>I thank you Sir, come brother now to make all friends.</p>
                     <stage>a dance</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>They dance.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ship.</speaker>
                     <p>Now lets in and drink each others health in</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Sack which the Gods did</hi> Nectar <hi>call,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>So end our mirth in a high Festival.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt</stage>
               </div>
               <div type="scene">
                  <head>Scene Ult.</head>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:51398:29"/>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Radamon <hi>apparelled like a Gentleman and</hi> Shiptons <hi>Maid with a pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſe of Gold in her hand.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                     <p>TO be ſure ſir the next Nap ſhe takes if I get not the jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ut her Neck from her: I dare promiſe to give you your purſe of gold agen, and that would go a little againſt my conſcience.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                     <p>Be very vigilant and fail not, then ile make thee Miſtres of all I have promiſed thee.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                     <p>Eſpecially for my having you ſir for my Husband.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                     <p>O I can't avoid that, I love thee too well my pritty ſmug face,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                     <p>I thank you ſir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                     <p>But I may ſtay thee too long, thou maiſt miſs an oppotunity: fail not to meet at the place I've appointed thee.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                     <p>Truly ſir I will not,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                     <p>Sure this plot cannot fail, which that it may not</p>
                     <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Ile to all my charming conſpiraces Will bend,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Shipton <hi>thou wilt hardly ſhun Hell in the end.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit <hi>Radamon.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                     <p>Now let me conſider of the preferment that will quickly fall upon me, muſt I that have been obeyſive to an old womans hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour become a Miſtris of command: muſt I that have ſcoulded, nay many times ſcufled for a penny, become Miſtris of a purſe of Gold? muſt I that have many times ſtole out in an even to kiſſe an Hoſtler, be embraced by a Gentleman, a handſome Gentleman; with a fine head of hair, neat body, ſtraight leg, nay and another pritty proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty worth all the reſt, and then thou art fitted for a Husband <hi>Abigal</hi> ile warrant thee. But I have heard our next neighbour goody <hi>Belch</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten complain of her Husbands beating her, but I ſaith ile pummel my
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:51398:29"/>Gentleman if he beats me, but let me ſee, I muſt finde out a gate to carry out my Gentility, will this Gate do?</p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ks abou</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <p>No it ſents too much of the ſerving maid, well then ſo</p>
                     <stage>walks agen</stage>
                     <p>No I ſtretch out my belly too much and that needs not, for my Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band does promiſe to get me with child quickly, and then e'faith my belly will ſtretch out it ſelf.</p>
                     <p>O this then will ſerve</p>
                     <stage>walks agen.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Shipton.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ship.</speaker>
                     <p>Ha! huswife is this your making haſte when I ſend you of an errand, what purſe have you got there? and what fine Gentleman are you to have for your Husband?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                     <p>Pray Miſtris be not angry and on my bended knees I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the ſtory.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ship.</speaker>
                     <p>Ceaſe that Ceremony and begin.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                     <p>Why truly forſooth at the Corner of this field I met with a very Gallant Gentleman who gave me this purſe of gold, and promiſed to morrow morn to marry me, if I would but ſteal that jewel about your Neck from you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ship.</speaker>
                     <p>Indeed forſooth, well open your purſe and tell your gold.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                     <p>O heaven Miſtris 'tis all ſtones and dirt,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ship.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes and he that gave it thee a Devil, for none elſe would inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate thee to rob me of this jemne of my true happineſs.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
                     <p>A Devil! O how I find my fears encreaſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ship.</speaker>
                     <p>Go in Girle ile follow and protect thee.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Maid.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ship.</speaker>
                     <p>This was <hi>Radamons</hi> device: but arm me ſtill ye powers de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine that no Devils inſtigation does betray me: protect me even now for I find a ſudden ſlumber ſeizes me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>[Soft Muſick and in Angel deſcends with a Book.]</hi>
                     <l>Shipton <hi>deſpair not but in hope grow ſtrong.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thou ſhalt find Mercy though thou haſt done wrong!</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Read ore this book and in it thou ſhalt find</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The ſumme of thy deſire to free thy mind.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:51398:30"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>From fear, thy ſoul ſecure from harm</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Of any Devils! 'tis a happy charme!</hi>
                     </l>
                  </stage>
                  <stage>[<hi>The Angels aſcends and</hi> Shipton <hi>wakes.</hi>]</stage>
                  <p>Ha! what's this a book? the cover bears the type of innocence, ile ok in it.</p>
                  <p>Shipton</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In thy ſorrows be not drown'd</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>From above thou hast mercy found:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Think not repentance comes too late</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>If 'tis unfeigned thou art fortunate!</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And though the Devil does endeavour</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To entrap thy ſinful ſoul, yet never</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Yeild, but his attempt reſiſt,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And he his ſuit will ſoon deſiſt.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>O endleſs comfort! now attempt what you can proud Devils, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>s! what noiſe is this?</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Pluto <hi>and all the Devils.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Well your buſineſs now? you ſee I do not quake</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That ere while made you and your Furies ſhake.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Plu.</speaker>
                     <p>Wee know thy power and thy magick skill, and for the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaſe of the ſame, we preſent thee with this paper wherein is a ſpell of Propheſie to fore tell of what was, what is, and whats to come. In his paper there is another ſpell powerful to command any ſpirit of w at nature ſoever,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Skip.</speaker>
                     <p>Well I accept your preſents but ſpurn at your ſociety, all your emptations are airy and too weak to beſiedge my fortyfied ſoul.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Plu.</speaker>
                     <p>Was ever Devil gull d ſo:</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>VVell lets deſcend and all Hell ſhall howl</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>This full fortnight for loſſe of</hi> Shiptons <hi>ſoul.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[<hi>Exeunt</hi> with horrid Muſick.]</stage>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:51398:30"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ship.</speaker>
                     <p>So let them roare.</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>VVhilſt I do all their Helliſh Acts deſpiſe</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The higher powers make me truly wiſe.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="epilogue">
            <head>The Epilogue.</head>
            <l>NOw you have taſted of our homely chear,</l>
            <l>Pray tell us how you like it: was it dere?</l>
            <l>Or elſe where lay the fault? pray gallants tell,</l>
            <l>If't did diſpleaſe t'was ill, if not 'twas well,</l>
            <l>But may the Ladies ſmile on't i'm ſure then,</l>
            <l>'Twill be approved off by the Gentlemen!</l>
            <l>So pleaſing both we are in hopes we may</l>
            <l>Expect your company another day.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="epilogue">
            <head>An after Epilogue ſpoken by <hi>Shipton.</hi>
            </head>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:51398:31"/>
            <l>IV'e ſcap't the Devil but I fear you moſt,</l>
            <l>If your frowns appear poor <hi>Shiptons</hi> loſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </l>
            <l>But now I look agen, methinks I ſpy</l>
            <l>A gentle pardon in each gratious eye.</l>
            <l>Viſit me oftner and in time you'l ſee</l>
            <l>Poor <hi>Shipton</hi> may deſerve your <hi>plaudite.</hi>
            </l>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:51398:31"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
